let set6=
[
    {
        question:`1. Consider the following assertions, in the context of Vegetative Propagation:
        1. Plant produced by vegetative propagation take less time to grow.
        2. Plants produced by seeds bear flowers earlier than those produced from vegetative propagation.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: There are several ways by which plants produce their
        offspring. These are categorised into two types:
        A. Asexual
        B. Sexual reproduction.
        In asexual reproduction plants can give rise to new plants without
        seeds, whereas in sexual reproduction new plants are obtained from
        seeds. Vegetative propagation It is a type of asexual reproduction in
        which new plants are produced from roots, stems, leaves and buds.
        Plants produced by vegetative propagation take less time to grow
        and bear flowers and fruits earlier than those produced from seeds.
        The new plants are exact copies of the parent plant, as they are
        produced from a single parent.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`2. Consider the following assertions in terms of fertility in
        various organisms:
        1. Reproduction in yeast takes place through budding.
        2. Reproduction process in algae takes place through fragmentation.
        3. Plants such as moss and fern also reproduce by means of spores.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A.1 and 2 only',
'B.2 and 3 only',
'C.3 only',
'D.1, 2 and 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation:
        1. Yeast is a unicellular organism in which reproduction is done
        through budding.The small bulb-like projection coming out from the
        yeast cell is called a bud. The bud gradually grows and gets detached
        from the parent cell and forms a new yeast cell. The new yeast cell
        grows, matures and produces more yeast cells.
        2. The process of reproduction in algae is done by fragmentation. In
        this process, the algae (such as spirogyra) breaks up into two or
        more fragments. These fragments or pieces grow into new
        individuals.
        3. Plants such as moss and ferns, also reproduce by means of spores.
        When spores are released they keep floating in the air reaching long
        distances. Under favourable conditions, a spore germinates and
        develops into a new individual.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`3. In the context of pollination in plants, consider the following
        assertions :
        1. Pollination of pollen grains is done on the stigma of flowers from
        the pollinators.
        2. If the pollen lands on the stigma of the same flower or another
        flower of the same plant, it is called cross-pollination. When the
        pollen of a flower lands on the stigma of a flower of a different
        plant of the same kind, it is called self-pollination.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: Since pollen grains are light, they can be carried by
        wind or water. Insects visit flowers and carry away pollen on their
        bodies. Some of the pollen lands on the stigma of a flower of the
        same kind. The transfer of pollen from the anther to the stigma of a
        flower is called pollination.
        If the pollen lands on the stigma of the same flower or another
        flower of the same plant, it is called self-pollination. When the
        pollen of a flower lands on the stigma of a flower of a different
        plant of the same kind, it is called cross-pollination.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`4. Which equipment measures the distance covered by a vehicle?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Odometer',
'B. Speedometer',
'C. Accelerometer',
'D. Altimeter',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation:
         The device which measures the distance covered by the vehicle is
        called odometer.
         Speedometer records the speed directly in km/h.
         Accelerometer is an instrument for measuring the acceleration of
        a moving or vibrating body.
         Altimeter is an instrument for determining altitude attained,
        especially a barometric or radar device fitted in an aircraft.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`5. In the context of magnetic and heating effects of the electric current, consider the following assertions :
        1. The wire gets hot when an electric current passes through it.
        2. When electric current passes through a wire, it behaves like a magnet.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanation: The wire gets hot when an electric current passes
        through it. This is the heating effect of the electric current.
        Oersted observed the deflection of compass needle every time the
        current was passed through the wire. So, when electric current
        passes through a wire, it behaves like a magnet. This is the magnetic
        effect of the electric current.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`6. What is the SI unit of electric charge?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Volt',
'B. Coulomb',
'C. Ampere',
'D. ohm',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: Electric current is defined as the rate of flow of
        negative charges of the conductor. In other words, the continuous
        flow of electrons in an electric circuit is called an electric current.
        The conducting material consists a large number of free electrons
        which move from one atom to the other at random.
        Since the charge is measured in coulombs and time in seconds, so the
        unit of electric current is coulomb/Sec (C/s) or amperes (A). The
        amperes is the SI unit of the conductor. The I is the symbolic
        representation of the current.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`7. What is the work done in moving a unit positive charge from infinity to that point in electric field called?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Electric potential',
'B. Potential difference',
'C. Electric current',
'D. Electric circuits',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: Electric potential, the amount of work needed to move
        a unit charge from a reference point to a specific point against
        an electric field. Typically, the reference point is Earth, although
        any point beyond the influence of the electric field charge can be
        used.
        The potential energy for a positive charge increases when it moves
        against an electric field and decreases when it moves with the
        electric field; the opposite is true for a negative charge. Unless the
        unit charge crosses a changing magnetic field, its potential at any
        given point does not depend on the path taken.
        Although the concept of electric potential is useful in
        understanding electrical phenomena, only differences in potential
        energy are measurable. If an electric field is defined as the force
        per unit charge, then by analogy an electric potential can be thought
        of as the potential energy per unit charge. Therefore, the work done
        in moving a unit charge from one point to another (e.g., within
        an electric circuit) is equal to the difference in potential energies at
        each point. In the International System of Units (SI), electric
        potential is expressed in units of joules per coulomb (i.e., volts), and
        differences in potential energy are measured with a voltmeter.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`8. The S.I. unit of force is:`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Kgm/s',
'B. Kgm/s2',
'C. Newton',
'D. Newton-meter',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanaton: Push or pull of an object is considered a force. Push and
        pull come from the objects interacting with one another. Terms like
        stretch and squeeze can also be used to denote force.
        In Physics, force is defined as: The push or pull on an object with
        mass that causes it to change its velocity.
        Force is an external agent capable of changing the state of rest or
        motion of a particular body. It has a magnitude and a direction. The
        direction towards which the force is applied is known as the
        direction of the force, and the application of force is the point
        where force is applied.The Force can be measured using a spring
        balance. The SI unit of force is Newton(N).
        In physics, motion is defined as the change in position with respect
        to time. In simpler words, motion refers to the movement of a body.
        Typically, motion can either be described as:
        1. Change in speed
        2. Change in direction
        The Force has different effects and here are some of them.
         Force can make a body which is at rest to move.
         It can stop a moving body or slow it down.
         It can accelerate the speed of a moving body.
         It can also change the direction of a moving body along with its
        shape and size.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`9. The rate of change of momentum of an object is proportional to:`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Mass of the body',
'B. Velocity of the body',
'C. Net force applied on the body',
'D. None of these',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanation: According to Newtons second law,
        The rate of change of linear momentum of a body is directly
        proportional to the external force applied on the body , and takes
        place always in the direction of the force applied.
        So the rate of change of momentum is Force i.e. Newtons second law
        helps us to derive an equation for force.
        Consider a body of mass’m’ moving with velocity’v’.Its momentum is
        given by p=mv…..(1)
        Let F be an external force applied on the body in the direction of
        motion of the body.Let dp is a small change in linear momentum of
        the body in a small time dt
        Rate of change of linear momentum of the body =dp/dt
        According to Newtons second law , F is directly proportional to
        dp/dt
        F=k*(dp/dt),where k is contant of proportionality
        F=k*(d(mv)/dt), F=km(dv/dt)
        But dv/dt=a, the acceleration of the body so, F=kma…….(2)
        the value of k depends on the unit adopted for measuring the force
        .Both in SI and cgs systems , the unit of force is chosen, so that the
        constant of proportionality (k) is equal to 1.
        from equation(2)
        F=ma…….(3)
        `
    },
    {
        question:`10. How many electrons taken together make one coulomb?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. 6.25 * 10^18 electrons',
            'B. 3.25 * 10^18 electrons',
            'C. 2.25 * 10^18 electrons',
            'D. 4.25 * 10^18 electrons',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: First of all, even infinite no. Of electrons can't be
        summed up to 1 Coulomb, what you actually mean is -1 Coulomb.
        We know that, Charge on 1 electron = -1.6 × 10^-19 Coulomb,
        Now, simple application of unitary method,
        No. Of electrons on -1 Coulomb of charge = 1/(1.6×10^-19) = 0.625 ×
        10^19 = 6.25 × 10^18
        So, 6.25 × 10^18 electrons make up a total of -1 Coulomb of charge.
        `
    }
]